<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the good and euell tounge With the vnstablenesse of the same, and also with the abuses thereof. With a discourse of the punishment which the Lord hath shewed on al those which through swearing and periuring themselues, haue broken Gods commandements: as by this treatise most plainely appeareth. Made by Iohn of Marconuille gentleman.</title>
            <author>Marconville, Jean de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854887</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854887</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 478:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the good and euell tounge With the vnstablenesse of the same, and also with the abuses thereof. With a discourse of the punishment which the Lord hath shewed on al those which through swearing and periuring themselues, haue broken Gods commandements: as by this treatise most plainely appeareth. Made by Iohn of Marconuille gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Marconville, Jean de.</author>
                  <author>T. S., fl. 1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[58] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Wolfe] for Iohn Perin dwelling in Paules Church yard at the signe of the Angell and are there to be sold,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1592]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and estimated publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: T.S.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶ (-D6).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swearing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE <hi>of the Good and euell <hi>Tounge.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the vnſtableneſſe of the ſame, and alſo with the abuſes thereof.</p>
            <p>With a diſcourſe of the puniſhment which the Lord hath ſhewed <hi>on al thoſe which through ſwearing and periuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, haue broken Gods commandements: as by this Treatiſe moſt plainely appeareth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by</hi> Iohn <hi>of</hi> Marconuille <hi>Gentleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prouerb. 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Man intendeth in his hart, but the aunſweare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the tounge is in Gods hand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at</hi> London <hi>for</hi> Iohn Perin <hi>dwelling in Paules Church yard at the ſigne of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell and are there to be ſold.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>T.S.</hi> to faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Reader greeting.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eeing entreated by a freend of mine (<hi>Gentle Reader</hi>) to peruſe this pamflet, and write ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in the behalfe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: I was contented, after the reading ouer of the ſame, to ſatisfie that his honeſt requeſt, becauſe in my poore opinion, it is well worthie the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, and neuer more neede full (it at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time the like treatiſe was needeful) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now in this our ſo corrupt age, after ſo long ſincere preaching (the Lord be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayſed therefore) of the moſt holy &amp; glorious Goſpel of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. The matter conteined herein ſetteth forth vnto thee, how and in what maner thou ſhouldeſt vſe and rule they tongue, the good which commeth by the modeſt and holy vſage thereof, &amp; the euill and great danger which ariſeth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in the abuſe of the ſame both to body and ſoule. It were ſuperfluous for me to ſet downe here the infinite number of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of miſchiefe, which an euil tongue hath wrought, &amp; what good otherwiſe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing vſed in the feare of god it hath broght
<pb facs="tcp:20342:3"/>and wil alwaies bring, becauſe thou ſhalt find them in the reading hereof ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, both by the autority of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripturs, and alſo of other prophane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, although in very deede the firſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is moſt ſufficient.: &amp; therfore ſith the heathen who neuer knew god aright, (bicauſe they knew not his Chriſt, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; redeemer of al ſuch as faithfullye beleeue in him, and vnfainedly beleue his holy goſpell, &amp; practize the ſame in their liues &amp; conuerſation all the daies of their life) made ſuch lawes and ordinances for the puniſhing of vnruly &amp; blaſphemous tongues, ſome with marking in the face with hoat burning iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſome by the purſe and ſome by death, which is the iuſt lawe of the moſt high. Let vs chriſtians, or at the leaſt which beare the name of Chriſt, and would gladly ſo be called, take hede how we abuſe our tongues, either with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, periuries, flatteries, filthie &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable ſpeeches, curſings, raylings &amp; backbitinges, leaſt we fall into the hands of the moſt ſeuere &amp; iuſt iudge, who iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both iuſtly and rightly, either to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation, or els to perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction both of body and ſoule for euer. Wherfore I exhort and beſech al the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hereof, of what eſtate or condition ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20342:3"/>euer he or ſhe be, in the name of God the father &amp; of his ſon Ieſus Chriſt, to bring with them circumciſed eares and hartes, and perfect &amp; ſound iudgement, ſo that the things which they ſhal read herin, may take deepe roote in their hartes &amp; conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as ſeats ready prepared for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering &amp; amending of them ſelues in the reaſonable and holy vſe of their tongues, as may be to the glory of God, their euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort in Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of others with whom they ſhall be conuerſant. For the Lord God created all things in the world for the vſe and ſeruice of man, and man, to ſerue him alone, all the daies of his life in holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which ſeruice of his reſteth in the hart and tongue, for it is written, with the hart we beleeue vnto righteouſnes, and with the tongue we confeſſe vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And againe let your talke &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication be ſuch as may bring grace to the hearers: and againe, if any man ſpeake, let him ſpeake as the wordes of God, that is, let his communication be holy that it may edify thoſe which heare it, ſo that therby your heauenly father may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified: again be ye holy, bicauſe I your god am holy. But we for the moſt part are thankeful vnto his maieſtie neither in
<pb facs="tcp:20342:4"/>hart nor tongue, for his benefites recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; eſpecially when he feedeth vs, for euen then when we ſhould be moſt tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for our meates and drinkes, we poure out all the repaſt whole: moſt filthie, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable, beaſtly, &amp; blaſphemous talke, and he is no good companion forſooth, that cannot &amp; wil not do ſo, and by that mean in ſtead of glorifying his holy name we altogither blaſpheme it with our hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houndiſh tongues, &amp; yet we thinke they do vs great wrong, who wil not thinke &amp; account vs to be good Chriſtians, But if this be, to be a good chriſtians, then al the deuils in hell are ſuch chriſtians. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if anie man ſhal admoniſh thoſe that thus ſhal abuſe their tongues, they aske what haſt thou to do with my ſpeeches, &amp; as the prophet Dauid complained of the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the people in his daies, Pſal. 12. they ſay, our tongues are ours, wee ought to ſpeake, what Lord ſhall vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole? Furthermore, the tongue is the meſſenger of the hart, and whatſoeuer the hart imagineth the tongue vtte reth, ſo that by the talke of a man, is known what an hart he beareth, for it is ſaid, out of the aboundance of the hart, the tongue ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, wherefore (Chriſtian Reader) let vs ſo vſe our tongues as that God may
<pb facs="tcp:20342:4"/>be honored and ſerued by them: And marke I beſeech you, what commoditie ariſeth by the ſeruing of his maieſtie tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and duelie. Firſt this we knowe, that what ſoeuer paine an earthlie ſeruaunt taketh about the ſeruice of his maiſter, that, that his painefull ſeruice, turneth to the benefite of the maiſter: But he that ſerueth God, the more duetifullie and painefully he ſerueth him, the ſame his paineful &amp; diligent ſeruice turneth whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to his owne benefite: yea euen to the enheritaunce of the kingdome of heauen, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: one chiefe and ſpeciall point of which ſeruice conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the tongue. And thus much according to my ſimple skil, and not like any great clarke, haue I as briefe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as I might, giuen thee to vnderſtand how thou oughteſt to come prepared to the reading of this treatiſe, not ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie &amp; without ſome fruit, but with iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and vnderſtanding. Wherefore I beſeech thee thanke God, for the author hereof who hath offered this his trauell for thy benefite, that hee finding by his paynes taken, ſome good to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued thereby, it may the rather encourage him and others which trauell in the like caſes, to go forward in ſuch meaſures as
<pb facs="tcp:20342:5"/>the Lord God ſhall beſtowe on them in their well doing, to the glory of his moſt holy name, and benefite of his Church, And ſo for this time I leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord. T.S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A TREATISE OF THE</hi> good and euill tongue, by Iohn of <hi>Marconuile Gentleman.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Man intendeth in his heart, but the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of the tongue is in Gods hand.</q>
               <bibl>Prou. 16.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne of the principall pointes that maketh a wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be knowne, is rightly to gouerne his tongue, and aptly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct his ſpeech: for it is commonlie ſeene that the ſtroke of the tongue is more dangerous then the dent of the ſpeare. Inſomuch that this wound may eaſily be ſalued, but the hurt which the wicked tongue leaueth behinde him is alwaies incurable. Wherefore the ſage <hi>Sirach</hi> ſaith; That hee may be worthily cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted happy which neuer offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by his vnruly tongue. And this is hee which by
<pb facs="tcp:20342:6"/>the aſſertion of Saint Iames is iudged a perfect man.</p>
            <p>It is a thing by cuſtome incident to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine things, that from whence we cull any commoditie: from thence, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wee gather alſo manie miſhaps and miſeries, for as it is apparant that the ſtarres and celeſtiall bodies are moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the ſuſtenaunce of this our life: whereof dependeth all the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and inclinations of theſe inferior bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, yet out of them iſſueth extreeme ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie which wee may hardly auoid by any aduiſe, as when it happeneth vs to be borne vnder a peruerſe climate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation, through the beneuolence of the aire, wee drawe our breath, and enioy our vitall ſpirites, but when it is infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it fretteth euery corner full of mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wailings, and mortalities, men cannot want the diuers vtillities which the ſea and waters daily conueieth vnto them: yet when with might &amp; maine they ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount their appointed limits, they dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb facs="tcp:20342:6"/>many thouſandes in one moment, whereof the inhabitants neers the Riuer of <hi>Loire</hi> may be very good witneſſes by the inſpeakable loſſe which lately chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to them thereby, in the yeare of our Lord God. <hi>1570.</hi> The life of man cannot be continued without the vſe of fire, yet who can vtter the ſoden frights &amp; dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Tragedies which it hath brought forth of the earth, mother &amp; nurſe of all growing creatures, comes, ruines, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings, &amp; earthquakes, gapings, &amp; peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous exhalations, which ſore annoieth mankind: euen ſo is the tongue as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted, for if it be well guided there is nothing better, nothing more pleaſant: but if it be ſuffered to run at randon, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more perillous. The tongue God wot is a litle member of ſlender ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, notwithſtanding in it is conreined fire &amp; water, ſouerein ſalue &amp; deadly poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for in this world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a greater miſchief the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous tung, nor a more better thing then
<pb facs="tcp:20342:7"/>friendly wordes and workes agreeable to the ſame. For this cauſe the renowned wiſe <hi>Byas,</hi> or as ſome others will haue it <hi>Pytacus</hi> ſent the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue of a certeine beaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> allotted to be ſacrificed to a King of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> called <hi>Amaſis,</hi> for the verie worſt and beſt member of the beaſt. Thereby to giue vs notice, that in a man nothing is more excellent than the vſe of a wel tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered tongue, nor nothing more villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous then a vyperous tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Socrates</hi> the moſt vigilant Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, ſheweth howe on a daie <hi>Pambus</hi> a ſilly ſot deuoid of knowledge, bethought him to goe to a certeine famous Doctor to be inſtructed &amp; better furniſhed in his defects: who after he had heard the firſt verſe of the 38. Pſalme, &amp;c. I will direct my waies that I may not offende in my tongue, roſe vp vpon the ſodeine, tooke leaue of his maiſter and departed, ſaying; That he deſired to learne nothing more, ſo that he might accompliſh in his deedes the contents of this one verſe. Signifying
<pb facs="tcp:20342:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereby, that the chiefeſt perfection, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt propertie perteining to a man, is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orderate his tongue, for ouermuch bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is euer ſubiect to controlment, and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at warely weareth his tongue ſheweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mſelfe to be wiſe, and he that gards his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outh and tongue, gards his own ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> compareth theſe prating par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts to emptie veſſels, which being ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, yeeldes a lowder noiſe then thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich are wel fraught with good liquor. <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> in his booke dedicated to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onicus,</hi> ſaith; That there are two times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for talking, the one when neceſsitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth vrge vs, the other whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth of that whereof he is verie wel skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It was obiected to <hi>Cherillus</hi> for what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe <hi>Lycurgus</hi> had made ſo fewe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ances. Hee replied, that the multitude of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wes and ſtatutes was nothing needfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o men that are ſpare of ſpeech. Wee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught by the Phyloſopher <hi>Zenon,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ature hath giuen vs two eares to heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur fill, but one onely tongue to ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:20342:8"/>ſeldome. Whervnto accordeth S. Paul ſaying; <hi>Bee you quicke in hearing, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlowe in ſpeaking. Sueton,</hi> alſo recorde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the principall cauſe whereof <hi>Oct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian</hi> aboue all other fauoured and fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> was, for the great ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance hee vſed in his talke. <hi>Cicero,</hi> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth, <hi>Cato</hi> the Oratour, woulde neu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leaue in writing, anie his Orations: affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that if it chaunced him to repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ought that hee had ſaid, hee woulde n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be vpbraid with his writing, which he could not denie. <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor beein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſnapt at for his too much ſobrietie i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> talke, inſomuche that his taciturniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was of moſt men thought worthie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprehenſion, aunſwered, that the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his peace ſhould not offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man, conſidering his life was inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and altogither without blame, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then hee vſed to ſpeake when he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might, or longe bee ſilent. Into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame reproach fell <hi>Heckades,</hi> anoble O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour of <hi>Greece,</hi> becauſe hee ſat mute
<pb facs="tcp:20342:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeing inuited to a ſolemne banquet where others chatted and iangled out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſure, which <hi>Archidamidas</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, aunſwered in the behalfe of <hi>Hec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ades</hi> to him that ſcoffed him for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing his peace. Art thou ignorant ſaide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee that thoſe which can wiſely ſpeake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an alſo warely holde their peace, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſee the times and tides not apt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lke.</p>
            <p>Hee therfore which will ſpeake, muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vel conſider before hee open his mouth, whither the wordes hee is about to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er may in time to come bee preiudiciall vnto him, hauing alwaies in minde the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncient Prouerbe; <hi>Lingua quò vadis:</hi> Tongue whither wilt thou.</p>
            <p>Amongeſt many goodly examples of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo much talke, that which is written of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Poet <hi>Ibyque</hi> ſeemeth verie fit for our purpoſe, who beeing ſharpely aſſayled and beſette on all ſides, with a route of careleſſe and royſting robbers, in a
<pb facs="tcp:20342:9"/>place far ſecluded from ſucker where he could not be ſeene or heard of anie man the poore Poet, this diſtreſſed <hi>Ibyque,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe readie to bee ſacrificed, no knowing where to complaine &amp; appeal for iuſtice, ſawe a company of Cranes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the aire, to whom he called aloud, O you Cranes be you witneſſes of the fraud and villany that I here receiue: after his death all paſſed a long time before it could<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bee knowne who was guiltie thereof, till on a diſmoll day that men aſſembled themſelues to a Faier, where alſo the murtherers of <hi>Ibyque</hi> made their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearaunce, it chaunced that at the ſame time certeine Cranes came that way, one of the ſame murderers ſmiling ſaid to his companions, behold where flies the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Poet <hi>Ibyque,</hi> which thing being noted of one that ſtood by, ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them of the fact committed: wherof inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent he aduertiſed the Magiſtrats, the murderers were apprehended, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the deed, and were executed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:20342:9"/>which happened only by their chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnaduiſedly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>The verie like hiſtorie we read in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> of certaine ſacriligious perſons, which by night had ſpoyled the temple of Pallas in <hi>Lacedemonia:</hi> the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after this hainous offence heard of, was found an emptie flagon in the porch of the Temple, and as men made their recourſe thither to beholde this pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpectacle, they debated among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues what this Flagon ſhould ſignifie, then one of the malefactors which was in the thronge, yet vnknowne, ſayd, my friendes giue mee leaue and I will ſhewe you my cenſure vpon this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as I geſſe this thing is happened for that thoſe whiche haue taken vpon them to robbe this Temple, fearing to bee attached in dooing the treſpaſſe, had drunke of a certeine confection called Cyge, which is a kinde of mortall poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to the ende they might bee quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie diſpatched out of the waie, and not
<pb facs="tcp:20342:10"/>to be brought to the place of iudgement and infamie of the worlde, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſhoulde incurre. But if it ſo chaunced that they atchieued their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe without beeing diſcouered, they had brought alſo with them a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſon Cyge, which is wine without water. And for this cauſe I thinke the Flagon is here left voide, Certeine of the aſsiſtance marking this deuice, iudged him to be a partner of the practiſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to warde, who vpon ſtraite examination, was founde culpable, and had the rigour of the law for his enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous guilt, whereof hee might thanke his incontinent tongue.</p>
            <p>At London in Englande, an accident not vnlike to the former, happened of a theefe, which in the depth of the night had craftely conueyed himſelfe into a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens houſe, minding to make ſpeedie diſpatch of the beſt wares that came next to hande, but hee coulde not ſo couertly handle the matter but the neighbours
<pb facs="tcp:20342:10"/>there adioyning, heard him burſling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the doore, which immediately aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled themſelues to take the theefe that was yet in the houſe, hee ſeeing this tumult to bee rayſed for his apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, cunningly got himſelfe in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the preaſe, buſily crying and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for the theefe: Inſomuche that the neighbours thinking him to be ſtopped, began to retyre homewarde, when this frantike fellowe coulde no longer holde, but muſt needes ſay, farewell theefe, the deuil goe with thee, for I haue loſt my hat in ſeeking of thee. Wherevpon he was ſtrait clapt faſt, for one kept the hat which hee ſawe falling from the theefe as hee fledde, which beeing laide to his charge was ſo aſtoniſhed, that hee coulde not denie the facte, and was hanged therefore at Tyborne, which hee might haue auoyded eaſely if hee had beene ſilent. King <hi>Seleucus</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Galyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> for his noble and valiant proweſſe in
<pb facs="tcp:20342:11"/>feates of armes, but as all humaine thing are full of fragilitie and mutations, ſo on a time it happened, that <hi>Mars</hi> which earſt was his gracious guide, ſo vnlucke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lye lowred and thundered his threate vpon this vnhappie Prince, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcomfited in a great conflict, was driuen to breake his Diademe, the onely enſigne of his Princely pompe, and to get him packing with three men, onely that hee might not be knowne. After he had wandred a while in the deſolate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertes, hee chaunced vpon a poore cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, where hee requeſted bread and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle water, to the ende hee woulde not bee reuealed, his Hoaſt ſhewed him all the comfort and curteſie that in him laie, knowing full well that it was the King, and did conduct him in the waie that hee did require: who ſurely ſhould haue gayned thereby a rewarde merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious for his trauayle, had not his tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiue tongue marred all his market, the King departing ſaid, farwel hoſt, the pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh
<pb facs="tcp:20342:11"/>wretch aunſwered, God keepe you my Lord, whereat the King fretting, not minding to be detected, made ſemblance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o offer his hande to his hoſe as though hee woulde take his hoſt coine, but it was a token to one of his men that hee ſhoulde cut off his hoſtes head, ſuch fruit we reape of our vnbrideled ſpeech.</p>
            <p>The euil that enſueth by an vndiſcreet tongue, hath a huge heape of more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which of purpoſe I let paſſe, that I might ſet out to the view, the hidden treaſure and gallant company that ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie embraceth, amongeſt whome <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyrius</hi> hath merited the preheminence. The Romane Senators had an auncient cuſtome, that one of their children ſhould attende on them in the Senate houſe, till the ſaid children paſſed the age of ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares, to this end, that they beeing inured to the holſom ordinances, of their anceſtors, might after be the more fit for the regiment of their country. Now it ſo fell out that the Senate on a time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed
<pb facs="tcp:20342:12"/>of a verie weightie matter, and ſtraigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> charge was giuen that it ſhould bee kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cloſe, where amongſt the other youthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this little <hi>Papyrius</hi> was alſo preſent: o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom when he came home, his mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> demanded what great matters had cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Senate that day to ſit ſo long. Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto hir ſonne replied that he might no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo doe, for he had commiſsion to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie, and as women are euer curious to knowe, ſhee allured hir little ſonne with fair promiſes, but therin ſhe loſt hir labor wherfore ſhe vſed thumps &amp; threates o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all ſorts to get this hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myſterie, which <hi>Papyrius</hi> perceiuing, practiſed a pretti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> policie, ſaying to his mother, that the thing which ſo much encombred the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate was, that euery man ſhould hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haue two wiues, when the mother heard this, ſhe ſtaied no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, but inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent aduertiſed the other Roman dames therof, that ſo vniuſt an ordinance might not go forward: the next morning at the gate of the Senate, were aſſembled great
<pb facs="tcp:20342:12"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oupes of matrons. Who inſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought, that in Rome ſuch inequalitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight not take place, for one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye with two wiues, affirming that it were much more expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould haue two husbands, the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors abaſhed to ſee this inciuilitie in their wiues, wondred from whence it ſhould proceede, but by any meanes they coulde not gather the cauſe hereof: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> litle <hi>Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> ſtepped forth &amp; bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee quiet, deciphering from pointe to pointe, what had hapned between his mother &amp; him, and how for dead of hir hee was driuen to vſe this deceit. The Senate highlie commending the wiſedome &amp; conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of this youth, ordeined that their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould no more approch the Senates houſe, except only young <hi>Papyrius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſecretes of the Senate ſhould not be reuealed, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Papirius</hi> was inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with a garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t called Pretext, which was the greteſt honor that he could haue
<pb facs="tcp:20342:13"/>in thoſe young yeeres to weare the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bite of a Senator. And this is reported o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Aullius Gellius</hi> and <hi>Macrobius</hi> in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saturnals.</p>
            <p>Alexander the great, hauing red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> letter of great importance in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his friend <hi>Epheſtion,</hi> which he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receiued from his mother, clapped his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vpon his mouth, meaning thereby that he to whom any ſecret thing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ought alwaies to haue his mouth cloſed. K. <hi>Licimacus</hi> offred to the Poet Philippide al that lay in his power to do, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Poet ſaid; My Lord the beſt benefite I can receiue of you, is neuer to know your ſecrets: this thing was not ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued of <hi>Fuluius,</hi> who knowing a great ſecret of the Emperour <hi>Octauius,</hi> did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it to his wife, &amp; ſhe diſcloſed it to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others which hir husband often laid reprochfully to hir charge: whereof ſhee being impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in a frantike fury ſlue hir ſelf, ſo did hir husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Fuluius.</hi> An exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple not far vnlike to this, is recited by <hi>Pliny,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20342:13"/>of the Philoſopher <hi>Anazerxes,</hi> who be reft himſelf of his tunge, &amp; teeth alſo, that he wold not reueal a certain ſecret which the tyrant <hi>Nicocrion</hi> ſought violently to wreſt from him. The like we reade of <hi>Zenon</hi> a Philoſopher, which choſe rather to cut of his tongue, then to diſcloſe his freendes councell. The <hi>Athenians</hi> made an Image of the duſt of a Lioneſſe, in the remembrance and honour of a certaine wanton woman called <hi>Lioneſſe</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing familiar company with <hi>Harmodius</hi> and <hi>Ariſtogidon,</hi> tyrants and enimies to the <hi>Athenian</hi> eſtate, concealed from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a certaine couert conſpiracie, for which cauſe ſhe is pictured without any tongue, to giue notice of hir ſecrecy. The ſeruants of <hi>Plocius Plancus</hi> as <hi>Valerius</hi> writeth, endured ſharpe torments and ſtrappadoes becauſe they would not vtter where their maiſter had hid him ſelfe to his enimies, who ſought to haue ſlaine him. <hi>Acgiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> king of <hi>Sparta</hi> greatly marueiled when it was told him to a condemned
<pb facs="tcp:20342:14"/>man which for anye crueltie that was done vnto him woulde neuer ſpeake a worde. The ſeruant of Cato the orator, hauing ſeene a certaine treſpaſſe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his maiſter, to the death woulde neuer vtter it. A Romaine <hi>Tribune</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded on a time of <hi>Metellus</hi> a valliant captaine, what hee ment to do concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a conflict which was at hande: He aunſwered, if I knewe that my ſhirt had intelligence of that I pretend to do, I would ſtraight waies caſt it in the fire. When <hi>Darius</hi> was ouerthrowne and vanquiſhed by <hi>Alexander,</hi> conueied him ſelfe into a cloſe corner, they which ſaw this, and knewe where he was, woulde not bewray him, although they ſuffered the moſt bitter paines that could be inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Horace</hi> amongſt his conuiuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions willeth that euery man ſhould kepe cloſe that which is ſaid and done at bankets.</p>
            <p>It was a cuſtome among the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that when they were aſſembled at
<pb facs="tcp:20342:14"/>a feaſt, the graueſt man of them all did alwaies keepe the dore: ſaying to them that entred there, take heede ſirs that not one word be blowne abroad, of all that is done here. The order of <hi>Pithagoras</hi> diſcipline was chiefely to inure his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to ſecrecie, to the which ende a long time they kept ſilence, and he had neuer any Scholer but he ſat mute two yeares at the leaſt: that thereby they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſtomed to ſecretnes, might learne neuer to ſpeake, but when neceſsity did compell them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> being asked what was the moſt difficult thing for a man to rule, (ſayde) to holde his peace. Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> amongſt the principall groundes of vertue hath placed <hi>Taciturnitie.</hi> The ancient Egiptians reuerence <hi>Harpocrate</hi> for the god of ſecrecy. So did the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines <hi>Angenora</hi> as goddeſſe of the ſame ſilence, whom they painted, cloſing her mouth with her fynger, in token of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:15"/>
            <p>For to conclude this matter of ſilence, <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> ſheweth vs that the Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cians had a cuſtome which might not be broken, which was, to puniſh aboue all offenders, him that had bewraied anie ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret committed vnto him: Further, ſuch is the prouidence of nature in the ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our members, that ſhe hath aſſigned to ech one his right roome, aſwell for the dignitie and decoration of the bodie, as for the commoditie and vſe of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. The braine which is the very feate of reaſon, the moſt worthie part of man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is placed all aloft in the head, as in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall throne, there to preſcribe and beare rule ouer the inferior partes: the tongue which is the interpreter of the inwarde thoughtes of the hart, is ſetled in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of both, to the ende it ſhould be vnder the braine, and not far from the hart, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo the ſame nature hath encloſed and hedged in with teeth and lips, as it were within a defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible bulwarke, that it might not be ranging vnaduiſedly: for this cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:20342:15"/>the Poet <hi>Heſiodus</hi> compareth the tongue to a hidden treaſure, which ſhould not be vſed, but when neceſſitie doth conſtraine. The Prophet Eſay reioyſeth aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the good gift he had in his toung: ſaying, God hath giuen mee a pleaſant tongue, a tongue rightly inſtructed, that it ſhould declare his words in due and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient time, to the comfort of them that be in miſery, but to the ſlothfull he hath framed my ſpeeches more pearcing then the two edged ſword. By our tongues ſaith Saint <hi>Iames</hi> wee praiſe God. To his purpoſe I remember a ſtorie of a man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to death, by an inferior Iudge, &amp; before his death to be bereft of his toung, the poore fellow appealed to the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Toloſa,</hi> there vttering his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble petitions ſaid: that the principall cauſe that moued him to appeale, was for that hee was condemned to haue his tongue cut off afore his death, which God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him to praiſe his name, &amp; that it were great wrong that he ſhould bee deſtitute
<pb facs="tcp:20342:16"/>of ſo good a member at the laſt inſtant of his life. Now if men maruell at a litle fiſh, called Remora, which is in length ſcarce halfe a foote, nor in breadth fiue inches, who notwithſtanding mauger the rage of the ſurging ſeas, and bluſtering winds is able to ſtay a ſhip in the middeſt of his courſe, as though it were tied faſt with an ankar. Then with more iuſt reaſon wee may wonder at the tongue, who being ſo litle a member can ſtir vp ſo manie mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of men, and incencing countrey, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt countrey, and Citie againſt Cittie, for this cauſe the Poets haue fained of old that <hi>Mercury</hi> had a magicall rod, called Caduſe: which in deede was nothing elſe but an eloquent tongue, whereby he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, or diſwaded men, at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe they ſayd of olde that Amphion forced great rockes to moue out of their place by the ſweete ſound of his Harpe. So did <hi>Orpheus</hi> cauſe okes and elmes to leape for ioy of his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb facs="tcp:20342:16"/>wherby it is ſignified that the ſwet melody of their cloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, could prouoke and ſtir vp the moſt lumpiſh dullards of the world. In like maner the ancient fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch men fayned, that one <hi>Hercules Selticus,</hi> who hauing a litle chain through the top of his tongue, wherunto was tied a great number of mens eares, he led them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſed him. Wherby he ment, that by the dexterity of his talke he made men to incline to what part he liſted. Some men attributed to <hi>Socrates:</hi> ſome to <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> ſuch a pleaſant toung, that they could transforme their hearers. And for this cauſe were called flexanimi, becauſe they turned the minds of men euen as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. By the benefite of the toung king <hi>Creſus</hi> ſon, who from his infancy hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bene mute, ſaued his fathers life, when a ſoldiar drew his ſword to haue laine him, not knowing that he was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing. The boy cryed out kill him not, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is my father. <hi>Methridates</hi> was a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prince, &amp; had notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vnder
<pb facs="tcp:20342:17"/>his dominion and obedience xxii. diuer languages which all he vnderſtood an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaue anſwere to ech one with an interpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor. The tongue of couetous <hi>Naball</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prouoked king <hi>Dauid</hi> to wrath, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tongue of ſage <hi>Abakell</hi> appeaſed him ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well, that he ſaid with a loud voice thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be to God that hath ſent thee this day be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore me, bleſſed be thy counſell, and tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo which haſt kept me this day from bloudſhed. <hi>Naaman</hi> of <hi>Siria</hi> returne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> homeward in a rage, becauſe the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had not healed him out of hande, but ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him to the riuer of <hi>Iordaine,</hi> for ſaid hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I haue in my countrey as good waters a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that of <hi>Iordaine,</hi> but his ſeruantes by thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holſome declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnto him made him of an other mind ſaying: if the prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had commaunded thee to do any grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> matter, without doubt thou wouldeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue done it willingly, but he ſaid onely waſh thee &amp; thou ſhalt be whole. Which <hi>Naaman</hi> putting in practise was cute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> incontinent. And by this we ſee the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20342:17"/>commoditie which commeth of a good tongue. Let vs therfore follow the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith: that no vnhoneſt talke, ſhould procede out of our mouths, that ribaldrie, wanton ſpeach, or fond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, ſhould not ſo much as be named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, but we ſhould rather accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome our ſelues to thankes giuing.</p>
            <p>Amongſt thoſe ſignes which acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them that rightly beleue in our ſauiour Chriſt, this in the ſcripture is reckoned for the chiefeſt: they ſhal ſpeake with new tongues. Now S. <hi>Peter</hi> doth teach vs that new language: when he biddes vs to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Ieſus Chriſt: who being iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with wordes, did not replie with the like: when he was ſlaundered &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, threatned not at al, but referred him ſelfe wholy to him that is the iuſt iudge. Whereof S. <hi>Paule</hi> being a right follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, writeth, we are ill ſpoken of, and wee bleſſe: we are perſecuted, &amp; we endure it patiently: we are maligned, and wee praye for them that taunt vs: we are made
<pb facs="tcp:20342:18"/>the outcaſtes of the world, and the moſt caitifes of al others, euen till this houre. Let vs conſider diligently that the tongue is giuen vs to praiſe and magnifie God. According to the example of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,</hi> who thanked God, that had giuen victory to <hi>Abraham. Delbora</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the people to praiſe God. So did ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> ſaying: bleſſed be God which is the father of our ſauiour Chriſt, father of the deſolate, and fountaine of all conſolation: we ought not onely to praiſe God, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be godly and vertuous men, as <hi>Dauid</hi> which praiſed the people in the name of God, after the Arke was brought vp and the ſacrifices completed. We haue a great number of exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples in the ſcripture, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that our toung was giuen vs to praiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and magnify God. <hi>Dauid</hi> praiſed god, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the promiſe of the Meſſias was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in him: who after his manifold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great tribulations, ſtill exalted the name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> god. So did <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne becauſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had builded the ſumpteous te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god
<pb facs="tcp:20342:18"/>The Apoſtles bleſſed &amp; praiſed god with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, attending for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the holy ghoſt. You ſee now to what end we haue the vſe of our toungs, which we ought to imploy to the ſeruice of god according to the examples of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Abraham</hi> praied for Iſrael, and was hard <hi>Moiſes</hi> requeſted pardon of God for the people, confeſſing the manifold bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites that God had beſtowed vpon them. <hi>Dauid</hi> praied that the bleſſing of God might be vpon his houſe. We are alſo commanded to praye, that the word of god and his truth might be ſpread abroad &amp; haue his courſe throughout the whole world. Beholde they are the fruites of a good tongue, to praiſe God, to bles God, to praye vnto him, and to inſtruct thoſe that are ignorant, for he that teacheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the way to righteouſneſſe, ſhall him ſelfe ſhine like a bright lampe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Now if we will be true followers of our Maiſter Chriſt, wee muſt acquaint our ſelues with that kinde of language
<pb facs="tcp:20342:19"/>and ſpeech which he alwaies vſed: for he preached and publiſhed the glory of god: he brought into the way thoſe that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; ſtraied, he reproued offenders, he ſturred vp the ſlothfull, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted thoſe which were in miſery, he praied for thoſe that were out of the way, he gaue thanks to God for all. Finally he had a modeſt tongue, pleaſant, gracious, amiable, and full of all conſolation. The Apoſtles after they had receaued the grace and vertue of the holy ghoſt, ſaid no more, but lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand &amp; we will make the fire to fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the skies, they ſtriued no more amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues for ſoueraignty, but ſpake new things, they vttred to the world the great wonders of god: but alas at this day we ſee the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary put in practiſe, for we indeuor to build againe the ancient tower of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, the tower of deadly ſtrife and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: when one ſort will needes be called euangeliſtes, and other reformed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, others entire and perfect proteſtants as though our ſauiour Chriſt were deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb facs="tcp:20342:19"/>and of diuers ſortes, &amp; as though the weete name of our redemer, were a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to ſcoffe at. In which behalfe we ſhall haue great neede of a newe Eſdras, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce againe this confuſion of tongues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o one Goſpell: Who as ſoone as certaine ſtrange women called Aſſotides, &amp; Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ites, had corrupted the hebrewe tongue, ſpeaking halfe hebrew, &amp; halfe like moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ites: the ſaid Eſdras brought it againe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ancient perfection. In like maner ſo many ſundry ſectes which are riſen vp in the Church of god repreſented to vs by their barbarous wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: haue ouerthrown &amp; marred the ſincerity of the Goſpel. Let vs therfore be no more followers of olde Adam, which caſt the faulte of his offence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wife Eue, &amp; ſhe threw it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rooked ſerpent: &amp; let vs take heede that we be not of the race of Caine, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ſlaine his brother, diſſembled the matter: but rather let vs follow the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teps of good king <hi>Dauid,</hi> which with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is humble ſpeech appeaſed the wrath of
<pb facs="tcp:20342:20"/>god: &amp; according to the aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of S. Paul, let our wordes be ſauored with ſalt, tending alwaies to the edification of our neighboures, &amp; that no wicked talke procede forth of our mouth. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſubmit our ſelues vnder the hande of God, to the end he may exalt vs in conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time: for he hath alwaies a ſingular regard to his ſeruants. Let vs expell and baniſh from vs all ſlaunder, &amp; backbiting, and cloſe our mouth with our hande, like to patient Iob: that no vndecent word iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue from vs at all, and when we talke, to ſpeake the wordes of God, which wee ought to vſe with feare, for when the words of god are ſpoken to the people vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aduiſedly, it brings them ſtraight to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. We are charged alſo to inſtruct our children, that they by thee may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, &amp; numbred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeruitude of Sathan, &amp; the better to accompliſh the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of god. Lo this is the thing wherunto a good tongue ought to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> employed, that it may bring forth the
<pb facs="tcp:20342:20"/>worthy fruites of iuſtice. But now it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me to ſpeake of the miſchiefe that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ens of a wicked tongue: it ſeemeth to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thing not from our purpoſe, firſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what the tongue is, to the ende the ſubiect whereof we treat, may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er vnderſtood. The tongue is a member of man, which is made of fleſh, and open, full of vaines, and ſinewes, becauſe of his great ſtirring and mouing, and chiefelye for the ſence of taſting, which is naturall and peculiar to the tongue, &amp; nature hath giuen it a humor which neuer wanteth, that is to ſaye ſpittle, which is nothing elſe but the excrement of fleame which floweth from the braine into the mouth, for a moyſture to the tongue: Which otherwiſe would ſoone waxe drye, by reaſon of his continuall mouing.</p>
            <p>Nowe the vſe of the tongue is to frame our wordes, and to helpe to chawe our meate, in the formyng whereof wee ought to conſider the great prouidence of God. For although the thought
<pb facs="tcp:20342:21"/>is the worthie part of the ſoule: yet what could it profite or auaile, if it had not the tongue for his interpretor? For this is he which ſetteth forth the knowledge of God. This is he which hath cauſed men to be aſſembled togither fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a brutiſh &amp; ſauege life, to humaine ſocietie: this hath erected villages, great cities, &amp; countries: this hath publiſhed and made known hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtatutes, and ordinances: and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all other things which are neceſſarye for vs. Wherfore we ought to knowe that the tongue was giuen vs, that by it we might know god, and to helpe one an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other by the communication of ſpeeches. Vnto theſe two purpoſes wee ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our talke. He then that will lead a proſperous life, &amp; ſee happy daies, let him kepe his tongue wiſely, and his lips that out of them proceede no fraud nor miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe: that he do good alwaies, &amp; ſeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peace, &amp; obtaine it. A holſome tongue which is not giuen to backbite, &amp; blame others, is the tree of life, pleaſant, and
<pb facs="tcp:20342:21"/>amiable to beholde: but frowarde talke maketh the ſoule ſad. A wiſe man is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſober in ſpeech. The foole when hee holds his peace, is oftentimes thought to be wiſe: the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue reſembleth a ſharpe pointed darte, if it bee not well ordered. Wherefore Saint Iames likeneth it to a fierce fire, for ſaith hee; <hi>An immoderate tongue filles the worlde full of iniquities:</hi> And this makes mee to remember the Philoſopher <hi>Anacarſis,</hi> who ſupping with <hi>Solon,</hi> as hee returned home was found ſleeping halfe the way, hauing one hande to his mouth, the other vpon his priuie partes, ſhewing theſe were mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers which woulde bee carefully looked vnto. For he that will be thought religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and refraines not his tongue, his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is not worth a dodkin. <hi>Amian,</hi> the compoſer of many prettie Fables, telleth one of a Satire, who beeing greeuouſlie annoied with extreame cold of rigorous winter, repayred by chance to a husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans houſe, there to warme himſelfe, and
<pb facs="tcp:20342:22"/>beholding his hoſt to blowe his handes, asked him wherefore hee did ſo, he ſaid, it was to heate his handes, not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when dinner was readie, hee ſawe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his hoſt buſily blowing his pottage, and againe he asked him the cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, his hoſt anſwered, that hee did it to coole his portage which was too hot, whereat the Satire diſdeining, ſayde, What ſir can you blowe hotte and cold both out of one mouth. Farewell fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, therefore, for I neuer ment to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſuche manner of people, whiche haue nowe one thing in their mouth, and by and by an other, and ſo he tooke his leaue of his hoſt, diſproouing alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither thoſe which haue two tongues, nowe praiſing a thing, and ſtrait way blaming and miſliking the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wherevnto accordeth the Prophete Iſaias, ſaying; That they are accurſed which affirme the thing that is euill, to bee good, and contrarie, good to be euill, conuerting light into darkeneſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:20342:22"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arkeneſſe to light, ſweetneſſe to ſower, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſower to ſweet, ſuch was the tongue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the wily Serpent, when he ſaid to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt parents, ye ſhal be like vnto the gods: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch was the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue of pernicious Ioah, who vnder the colour of faire wordes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue <hi>Amaſa</hi> traiterouſly, in ſaluting him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aining to giue him a curteous good eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Such was the tongue of rebellious <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> when hee ſo miſchieuouſly ſlue his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rother. And ſuch was the tongue of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he tooke his iourney to ſpeake euil of the people, had not his Aſſe repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him by the way. Such was the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue of <hi>Dalyla,</hi> when ſhe betraied <hi>Sampſon</hi> to the <hi>Philiſtians</hi> his enimies. And ſuch was the venimous tongue of the caitife Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, when hee deliuered the Sauiour of the world in kiſſing of him, to his dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foes. But none hath better diſcribed the miſcheefe of a wicked tongue, then the kingly Prophet Dauid, when hee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the malice of backbiters, ſaith; their mouth is ful of bitternes &amp; curſings,
<pb facs="tcp:20342:23"/>full of falſhood and deceit, and vnder th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tongue lurketh tedious ſtrife and debate they lye in ambuſh and oppreſſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, out of cloſe and couert corner they make a play game to bring to vtte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ruine thoſe which are deſolate. They watch continually for to intrap the ſilli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſort. They holde faſt in their gripes the poore caitiue, that thinkes no hurt. They ſay in their heart God hath forgotten all, he hath hidden his face and ſhall neuer ſee the thinges that wee doe. The ſame Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in an other place ſaith; Good Lorde deliuer me from lying lips &amp; ſlanderous tongues, for they are like vnto ſwift and ſharpe arrows, which are fet from a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and poyſant bowe. The Eccleſiaſticall ſtorie doth admoniſh vs to hate the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperer and tale teller, and ſpecially he that hath a double to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue. For herehence hath come the diſtruction, not of a few which earſt liued in peace and tranquilitie. This is it which hath turned vp and downe many ſtrong and defenſible Cities, hath
<pb facs="tcp:20342:23"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efamed many worthie perſonages, hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aken a ſunder a number of princely Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces, and hath incenſed to ciuill ſedition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any goodly countries. Whoſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndes a liſtening eare to theſe double <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ngues, or rather to theſe two edged wordes, ſhall neuer reſt in quietnes, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euer be at peace with any of his friends. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he laſh of the whip woundeth the fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it the ſtroke of the tongue breaketh the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one: the whip only perſecuteth our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on corpes, but the glike of a pernicious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongue doth eclipſe our bright renowne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd leaues a ſpot of blacke defame to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſteritie, which is more dangerous then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y hurt we can receiue in our body. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y men haue beene ſlaine by the edge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſworde, but many more by the pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng blowes of wicked tongues. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id Prophet concludeth that he is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect bliſſe, which hath not paſſed through his painfull Purgatorie of byting tungs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd hath quite eſcaped their fearefull fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie. For the death which commeth by yll
<pb facs="tcp:20342:24"/>tongues is maruellouſly to be feared, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> better it is to fall into any other kinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> death and daunger, then by that whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> comes hereby. For it is ſaide, that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which forſake our Sauiour Chriſt &amp; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> holy name, ſhalbe vexed heerewith, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe ſhall conſume &amp; extinguiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out reſtraint, &amp; it ſhalbe ſent againſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as a fierce Lioneſſe, &amp; ſhall deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a wild Panther. Therfore ſaith hee, hed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in thy lips with thornes, &amp; plant bars a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bulwarkes before thy mouth, that fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thence proceede no vndecent wordes, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God is the witnes of our thoughtes, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> true beholder of our hearts, &amp; the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all that which our tung bringes fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Now although the life of man be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect to ſundry ſortes of calamitie, yet n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reckening thoſe which comes by ſickn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, poiſons, lightnings, tempeſts, &amp; ſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſchances, notwithſtanding that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be founde any thing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtilleth more miſchiefe &amp; miſerie to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mane kind, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from a diſloiall &amp; deuil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20342:24"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongue. For ther is no kind of inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce that brings vnto vs a more mightie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea of miſchiefs of al ſorts, then wars. But were not malicious tungs the cauſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we ſhould ſurely haue no war at al, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are the trumps &amp; drums that ſtrikes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he alarum to all ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, It was theſe that pricked forth Alexander to many bloudie battels, promiſing him that hee ſhould be conqueror of the whole world. K. Pirrus alſo had diuers ſtingers &amp; buzzes in his eare, which babled nothing els but brauls and murders, whom the wiſe <hi>Cine as</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred and ouermatched. Who on a time ſeeing K. Pirrus preſt to bid battell to his enimies, asked him what hee ment to doe, ſeeing alreadie hee vanquiſhed the Romanes. I will aſſay my force ſaide he with the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> &amp; when you haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome <hi>Sicile</hi> ſaid <hi>Cineas,</hi> what then will you do? Pirrus anſwered, I will ſet vpon <hi>Lybia, Carthage,</hi> and <hi>Maceaonia,</hi> whiche yet remaineth vnconquered:
<pb facs="tcp:20342:25"/>and this atchieued ſaid <hi>Cyneas,</hi> what wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you then more: wee will ſaid <hi>Pyrrus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelues in ioy and ſolace, then <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> replied, &amp; I pray you ſir what haue you to doe with all this warre, that after them you may liue in reſt, whereas you may be in preſent quietneſſe and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. And by this ſound aduice the Kyng was quite diſwaded to make war vpon neighbors. If <hi>Fraunce</hi> during theſe ſtur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> die ſtirres, had had but one good <hi>Cyneas,</hi> that flouriſhing realme ſhould not haue beene ſo toſſed and turmoyled as wee ſee now, in ſuch ſort, that it is almoſt in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place ſparkled with humane bloud, ſo fiercely were they ſet on fire one againſt the other. But from whence I pray you came all this, but from ſeditious tongues: for a man might ſee diſſentious bookes Printed and ſowen abroade verie rife. Wherein was nothing leſſe treated of then peace, nor nothing more laboured then warre and iangling, ſo that had not GOD reſiſted their malice, you ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:20342:25"/>haue ſeene long or this the totall deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this goodly countrey. And if it happen that anie more of theſe bloudie Butchers and ſetters forth of al miſchief doe againe ſhewe their monſtruous heades, I wiſhe them no more harme, but that they may become as dumbe as euer was <hi>Iparkion,</hi> or that they might be bereft of their tongues as <hi>Zenon Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes:</hi> and to them that would reitterate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine this ciuill ſedition, might alſo bee void of hands to execute their wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as was the handes of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and might be as blind to go forward therein, as was <hi>Tyripe</hi> or <hi>Hipſe,</hi> and that they might not be able to goe no more, then was <hi>Myphiboſeth:</hi> that their Horſes might reſemble the fatall ſteede of <hi>Gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius Zoianus,</hi> &amp; that the Captaines might haue no more valure and force then euer had <hi>Eracinade,</hi> that the bootie and praie might be like to the gold taken from <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſa.</hi> In briefe I vow vnto them, all the execrable curſes of <hi>Oedipus,</hi> and all thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20342:26"/>balefull bliſſes conteined in the Pſalme; Lorde doe not conceiue my praiſe, for ſurely they are not of GOD which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth peace, deſiring nothing els but blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die warre.</p>
            <p>He that will liue in continuall reſt and quietneſſe ſaith Dauid, let him take heede that his tongue ſpeake no hurt of others, and let him keepe his lips from lying and deceit. But to returne to our purpoſe of the miſchiefe that comes of euil tongues, Salomon ſaith; He that warneth wiſely his mouth, gardes his ſoule, but he that pratleth vnaduiſedly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s oppreſſed with manye miſeries. Iob calleth ſuch kinde of people forgers of Fables, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of Ieremy haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed their tongues to lye leudly, and haue imployed all their trauell to doe miſchiefe, yet ſome pleaſant compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there bee which accountes lying to be no ſinne, though Dauid ſaie, that all liers ſhal goe to vtter perdition. From an euill diſpoſed tongue, proceedeth not
<pb facs="tcp:20342:26"/>only lying but ſwearing, blaſphemyng, reproaches, ſcoffings and ſlanders.</p>
            <p>Reade ouer the auncient Chronicles, and among them all you ſhall not finde ſo many kinde of ſtraunge others as are nowe daily vſed amongſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, looke well about and you ſhal finde euerie corner full of periuries. It was an infamous thing amongeſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, if anie happened to ſweare by their falſe Gods, yet amongſt vs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians wee make it a play game to take the name of the eternall God in vaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> reciteth, that in times paſt it was not lawfull for litle children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within doores to ſweare by <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> or <hi>Dinis,</hi> but that they muſt go out of the houſe, that by this kinde of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, they might learne not to ſweare at all, or at the leaſt to bee moderate in their oathes. The auncient Byſhops of Rome which our aunceſtours long agoe called <hi>Famines</hi> or <hi>Diales,</hi> for feare
<pb facs="tcp:20342:27"/>durſt not ſweare at all, whatſoeuer dread or danger was offered them.</p>
            <p>On a time in <hi>Athens,</hi> acerteine Sorcereſſe accuſtomed to the <hi>Paynime</hi> ſacrifices, was inſtantly deſired and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted of all the people to curſe and call vengeance vpon <hi>Alſibiades,</hi> which then was verie euil thought of in <hi>Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> Wherevnto ſhe anſwered, that ſhee had receiued hir Prieſtly dignitie thereby, to conſecrate and bliſſe the people, and not wiſh hurt or vengeance to any, and ſo ſhe coulde neuer bee induced to ſpeake yll of <hi>Alſibiades,</hi> if wee laie aſide examples of infidelles, and conſequently to come to thoſe of the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Lewes</hi> did ſo abhor periurie and blaſphemie, that hee conſtituted a lawe, that whome ſoeuer was founde to bee a blaſphemer of Gods holie name, ſhould haue the Flower deluſe glowing hot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in his forehead, to the ende he might bee knowne of all men to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame and great ignomie and reproach,
<pb facs="tcp:20342:27"/>whereſoeuer hee came. It ſo chauneed that a certeine noble man of his Court being ouercome with coller, had ſworne vnaduiſedly, and as the officers woulde haue executed the rigour of the lawe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, manie of the peeres of the rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me withſtood it, beſeeching pardon &amp; grace of the King in his behalfe, but the King was no leſſe ſeuere in obſeruation of this his Edict. Then was that good King <hi>Seleucus</hi> in his Penall Statute made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt adulterers, who woulde haue pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his ſonne, for that hee had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed his ordinaunce: Euen ſo the ſaid King <hi>Lewes</hi> aunſwered, that he would himſelfe abide the payne conteined in his Edict, and that the ſaid marke ſhould bee fixed in his owne forehead, that all blaſphemies thereby ſhould bee baniſhed his realme. So the moſt Chriſtian King deſirous to put in practiſe the laudable conſtitutions inuented by his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, for the puniſhment of blaſphemie hath ordeined that no manner of perſon
<pb facs="tcp:20342:28"/>ſhoulde blaſpheme the name of GOD, or vſe any other execrable oathes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine and forfeiture to haue his tung pearced with a hot yron.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phillip</hi> an other of the French Kings, made a lawe, that if any whatſoeuer gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or ſimple, yea, although hee were in birth right noble, in what place ſoeuer hee were thought it were in, a common Tauerne where manie wiſe men forget themſelues, if hee blaſphemed Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie name, hee ſhould preſently be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour made a lawe, that whoſoeuer were apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a vaine ſwearer, ſhould leeſe and pay thirteene ſhillings foure pence, but if after hee woulde not bee ſorie for his offence, and willinglie paye the ſayde money, hee ſhould loſe his head. At <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binggen</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> a deſperate boy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed
<pb facs="tcp:20342:28"/>newe oathes, ſuche as were not in common vſe, but the Lorde ſent a Canker or ſome woorſe diſeaſes, and conſumed the inſtrument wherewith he blaſphemed God.</p>
            <p>But to goe beyonde men the Lorde himſelfe hath made a lawe, hee that blaſphemeth and taketh the name of the Lorde GOD in vayne, ſhall dye the death. Leuit. 24.</p>
            <p>That faithfull and good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Gods Churche Maiſter Iohn Foxe, from whome I collected this notable and woorthie hiſtorie, giueth a moſte gentle and fatherlike admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and warnyng vnto all young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen to leaue and vtterlye to forſake theire moſte extreame outragious and horrible ſwearyng, by the greate and fearefull example of theſe Gentlemen following.</p>
            <p>In the time and raigne of the moſt famous Kyng Edwarde the ſixt, there
<pb facs="tcp:20342:29"/>was in <hi>Cornewayle</hi> a luſtie young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who dyd ryde togither with other more Gentlemen, and their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes in number about twentie horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, amongſt whome this luſtie yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker entering into talke, began to ſweare moſt horriblie, among whome one of the companie not able to abide ſuche blaſphemous abomination, in gentle wordes ſayde to him, that hee ſhoulde giue an account for euerie idle worde, the Gentleman takyng ſnuffe thereat, why quoth hee takeſt thou thought for mee, take thought for thy winding ſheet, well quoth the other, take heede, for death giueth no warning, for as foone commeth a Lambes skinne to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket as an olde Sheepes: Gods woundes (quoth hee) care not thou for me, raging ſtill after his ſwearing maner worſe and worſe in wordes, till at length paſſing onwarde their iourney, they came ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ouer a greate Bridge which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:20342:29"/>ouer a peece of the arme of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a, vpon which bridge this gentleman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wearing, ſpurred his horſe on ſuch ſort, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he ſprang cleane ouer the bridge with the man on his backe, who as hee was going, cryed horſe and man and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the deuil. That priuate example which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appened to ſome eſpecial, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iculerly may conſider with him ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow common and great ſwerers are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. I could neuer yet either by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ience or reading find, but that they which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake delight in ſwearing, and vſed vainely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſweare, were greeuouſly puniſhed one way or another. For my part though I am of ſmall yeares and but young, yet I haue noted in ſome, that God will not ſuffer this vice to go vnpuniſhed. When I was in a certaine place for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings ſake, I knew a company of youthes which were very familiar, and would ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be a ſunder, they were ſo wickedly bent, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were met, one would haue ſuppoſed that a companye of young <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20342:30"/>two olde lecherous dotars, whom Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miraculouſly deliuered, for her innoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, by the helpe of young Danyell, who no leſſe ſtraight iudged and condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid olde wilye marchants, who lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ambuſh to oppreſſe the ſaid holy m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> trone. What ſhould I ſpeake of iuſt <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bothe,</hi> againſt whoſe innoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and periured <hi>Ieſabell,</hi> ſuborned two fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> witneſſes, they not onely to bereaue hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his vineyard, but of all his landes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> life alſo.</p>
            <p>O Lord increaſe the number of thy ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uantes, roote out vaine ſwearing and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iurie, conuert blaſphemers to the obed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of thy will, and aduaunce thy ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> name: who art to be glorified now and euer more, togither with thy Son our Sauiour, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20342:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
